Guide to the Arnold Johnson Papers TAM.137
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Arnold Johnson Papers
Bulk, 1951-1979
1926-1989
TAM.137
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
6.75 linear feet in 5 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, and 1 oversize box.
Arnold Johnson was a long-time Communist Party USA official. In 1932, he received a B.A. in Divinity from Union Theological Seminary and helped to organized Sherwood Eddy's "American Seminar in Europe." Later in life, he was a representative of the American Civil Liberties Union New Mobilization against the War in Vietnam. This collection consists of the personal papers of Arnold Johnson, and chiefly consists of course materials, speeches and statements, articles (primarily published in newspapers and Communist Party publications), correspondence, clippings, flyers and brochures, handwritten notes, photographs, and memorabilia spanning the years 1926-1989, with the bulk of the material covering the years 1951-1979.
Johnson, Arnold (Arnold Samuel), 1904-1989.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
These papers were given to the Tamiment Library on April 4th, 1989 by Aurelia Johnson. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1989.011 and 1989.012.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Arnold Samuel Johnson was born in Seattle, Washington on September 23, 1904, one of four children (3 boys and a girl). His parents, both Scandinavian immigrants, had met in a Michigan lumber camp. After moving to Seattle his father worked in the lumber mills of Washington; both parents were devout members of the Swedish Evangelical Church. As a young man Arnold Johnson was drawn to the christian socialist philosophy, and he became deeply commited to the plight of the working class. After becoming an active participant on behalf of workers his attitudes gradually changed. Acting on strong personal principles he moved away from religion in the traditional sense, but continued with his commitment to the working class.
He worked from the age of 12 in lumber related jobs but was still able to complete high school (in Hoaquim, WA), benefitting from having two older brothers working. The family moved to Los Angeles where Johnson briefly attended UCLA before he moved to Washington DC to study law in 1924. He attended the National University Law School but after a year returned to Los Angeles, with the intention of becoming a preacher, and entered California Christian College. He graduated with a BA in 1929 and moved to New York City to continue his religious education at Union Theological Seminary (UTS); at the same time he attended Columbia University Teachers College. In 1931 Johnson received a Masters Degree in Christian Education and in 1932 a bachelors of Divinity from UTS.
The summers of 1929 and 1930 when Johnson helped to organize Sherwood Eddy's “American Seminar in Europe”, and the summer of 1931, when he was involved in the National Miners' Union struggle in Harlan Kentucky, were formative experiences for Arnold Johnson. Even while he continued his Christian education he was moving away from the church as a means of effective social reform. The American Seminar, led by Sherwood Eddy, a preacher and lecturer on social questions, was attended by educators, writers, preachers and politicians. The seminar introduced the participants to prominent people in education arts and politics in London, Paris, Geneva, Berlin and Warsaw; the climax for Johnson was the final 2-3 weeks spent in the Soviet Union where he received his “first introduction to Communist thinking” and “saw socialism in construction.” (this and following quotations are from Johnson's notebook, Series V F. 19).
His first acquaintance with communists in struggle was in Harlan County, KY, where Johnson, a representative of the American Civil Liberties Union, spent 6 weeks in jail in company with striking miners. He was arrested (but never tried) for criminal syndicalism after distributing a pamphlet (by Roger Baldwin) on freedom of speech. He met communists (such as Jesse Wakefield) who were involved in the struggle of the miners. Johnson later felt that he “should have studied the role of the Communist Party and joined it at that time.”
Although he completed his studies, he decided in 1931 not to pursue a career in the church. Affected by his experiences in “bloody Harlan”, by the deepening national depression, and by the belief that the religious community was too often compromised by “idealism in the service of capitalism,” Johnson became involved in the unemployment movement. In 1932 he joined the Conference for Progressive Labor Action (CPLA) led by A. J. Muste. In 1933 he was appointed Ohio organizer of the Unemployed Leagues. Also in 1933 Johnson was elected secretary of the first National Unemployed League at a convention in Columbus, Ohio. He worked primarily in Ohio but also helped to organize the unemployed in Kentucky, West Virginia, and Pennsylvania. While in Ohio (in 1933) Johnson met and married Aurelia Ricci who was also involved with the unemployed leagues.
Between 1932 and 1936 the CPLA underwent name changes, program changes and mergers; Johnson became disillusioned with the lack of unity and the anti communist sentiment which was often an undercurrent in the movement. In 1936 he was influential in the merger with the communist organized unemployment councils to form the Workers Alliance; Johnson became national secretary of this group, and in the same year he joined the Communist Party. He later said of this decision “I cherish my membership with a certain positive pride and joy.” By 1936 he had become convinced that the Communist Party was the most sincere and effective battler for the rights of the unemployed. In addition the hope of a system of scientific socialism aimed at eliminating poverty, racial discrimination and war, strongly appealed to Johnson.
He continued working with the Workers Alliance after 1936 but also became increasingly involved in the running of the Ohio Communist Party. In 1939 he became state secretary and from 1940 to 1947 he was state chairman. He ran for office as a Communist Party candidate for Governor (1940), Mayor of Cleveland (1941), and Senator (1946); although not elected Johnson received substantial support in his runs for the Board of Education in Cleveland in 1943 and 1945.
In 1947 Johnson left Ohio for New York to become National Legislative Director of the CP. Gus Hall replaced him as chairman of the Ohio CP. During the next 32 years Johnson continued to dedicate himself to the communist cause. His wife Aurelia supported and joined him in this commitment. Although he never held key leadership positions in the Communist Party USA, Johnson did hold several high profile appointments which gave him considerable public exposure. In addition to his legislative work Johnson also became a representative of the Civil Rights Congress and later held office as Vice Chairman of New York State CP, Public Relations Director of the CPUSA and Chairman of the Political Action Commission.
As Public Relations Director Johnson received and responded to Lee Harvey Oswald's inquiries about CPUSA in 1963. He also represented the Communist Party in various peace coalition movements such as the New Mobilization against the War in Vietnam (New Mobe). He travelled extensively as a representative of the Communist Party, twice to Europe and the Soviet Union (1961 and 1966), and also to Cuba (1976) and the Democratic Republic of Vietnam (1975) for ceremonial occasions.
Johnson's activities on behalf of the Communist Party were interrupted on several occasions by federal investigation. The most serious being his Smith Act indictment at the height of McCarthyism in 1951. He was charged (along with 20 other leaders of the Communist Party) with advocating the overthrow of the government. In Johnson's case the evidence used against him centered around an article of his published in Political Affairs in 1949 “The Communists Fight for the Traditions of July Fourth” in which he quoted Abraham Lincoln “All that serves labor serves the nation. All that harms labor is treason to America.” Johnson was found guilty in 1953 and sentenced to 3 years in jail and a $6000 fine. After the appeal process had failed he was jailed in 1955 (January) and released after 2 years and 5 months in 1957 (May). Johnson was indicted on two other occasions, in 1962 under the McCarran Act, for refusing to register as a Communist Party member, and in 1970 by the House Internal Security Committee for refusing to cooperate with the investigation of the New Mobilization Against the War in Vietnam. Both these charges were later dropped.
Arnold Johnson retired from active involvement in the Communist Party in 1979 after a stroke and a heart attack had left him in ill health. Johnson died September 28, 1989, a few days after his 85th birthday.
CHRONOLOGY
1904 Born Seattle, Washington
1929 Graduated from California Christian College, Los Angeles, CA.
1929-30 Spent 2 summers as secretary and organizer for Sherwood Eddy's “AmericanSeminar” held in Soviet Union and Europe.
1929 Joined State Socialist Party in New York
1931 Spent the summer with coal miners in “Bloody Harlan” Kentucky as a representative of the American Civil Liberties Union, jailed for 6 weeks.
1932 Received Bachelor of Divinity from Union Theological Seminary, NY & MA from Teachers College, New York (1931).
1932-38 Moved to Ohio, became involved in local and national unemployed leagues and the Workers Alliance (1936).
1933 Married Aurelia Ricci
1936 Joined Communist Party (CP)
1939-47 State Secretary and then Chairman of the Ohio CP.
1940 Elected to Central Committee of CP
1947 Moved to New York to take the position of National Legislative Director of the CPUSA.
1950 Became executive of Civil Rights Congress
1951 Arrested and charged with conspiring to overthrow government (Smith Act).
1953 Sentenced to 3 years in Jail and a $6000 fine
1955-57 Imprisoned in the Federal Penitentiary in Petersburg, VA.
1958 Secretary of Public Affairs of the CPUSA
1960 Vice Chairman of New York CP.
1960 Peoples Right Candidate for Congress (New York, Washington Heights).
1961-66 Visited communist countries with Gus Hall
1962 Ordered by Subversive Activities Control Board to register as a member of a communist organization (McCarran Act)
1966- Public Relations Director for CPUSA.
1970, 1974 CP candidate for Senate in New York.
1970 Cited for contempt of Congress when he refused to testify before the House Committee on Internal Security (as a board member of New Mobilization Committee for Peace in Vietnam - New Mobe).
1960's & 70's Represented the CP in coalition peace movements such as New Mobe.
1975 Visited Democratic Republic of Vietnam
1975 Visited Cuba for the First Congress of Cuban CP
1979 Retired from active service with CP due to ill health.
1989 Died
Scope and Content Note
The most common types of material found in the collection are speeches and statements, articles (primarily published in newspapers and Communist Party publications), correspondence, clippings, flyers and brochures, handwritten notes, photographs, and memorabilia.
The collection provides insights into the development of Johnson's political thought and into his commitment to the Communist Party. The material also reflects his leadership responsibilities at the state level, particularly in Ohio, and at the national level. The speeches, statements, and clippings in particular document Johnson's broad involvement in the party; as Public Relations Director he was often spokesman and as such had a fairly high profile. The Smith Act indictment, and the consequences of this for Johnson, are of particular interest, and are also well documented, particulary through his prison correspondence with his wife Aurelia. Also of interest are the letters from Lee Harvey Oswald (1963). Although influential in his career, Johnson's visit to Harlan Kentucky in 1931, and his involvement with the Ohio Unemployed Leagues are not well represented in the collection.
Arrangement
Folders in Series I-V are arranged chronologically.
The files are grouped into six series:
Education and Political Thought, 1926-31
Early Political and Communist Party Activities, 1931-47
Smith Act and Consequences, 1947-57
Political Activities, 1957-79
Biographical.
Artifacts and Photographs
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Researchers interested in using audiovisual materials in this collection (films, cassette tapes, VHS tapes, et cetera) must use a digitized copy, which we refer to as an access copy. Researchers may view an item’s original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that already have already been digitized are noted in the collection’s finding aid and can be requested in our reading room; materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. These requests are free of charge and can be made in anticipation of your visit. The process typically takes four to six weeks. To request an access copy be made, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@library.nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A librarian will respond to you with further information.
American Civil Liberties Union.; California Christian College.; Citizens Emergency Defense Conference (New York, N.Y.).; Civil Rights Congress (U.S.).; Columbia University. Teachers College.; Communist Party of the United States of America (New York).; Communist Party of the United States of America (Ohio); Communist Party of the United States of America.; Conference for Progressive Labor Action.; Davis, Eugene; Dennis, Eugene, 1905-1961.; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; Eddy, Sherwood, 1871-1963.; Foster, William Z., 1881-1961.; Hall, Elizabeth; Hall, Gus; Johnson, Arnold (Arnold Samuel), 1904-1989.; Johnson, Aurelia Ricci, d. 1989.; McAvoy, Clifford T.; Meyers, George A.; National Miners' Union (U.S.).; New Mobilization Committee to End the War in Vietnam.; Ohio Workers Alliance.; Oswald, Lee Harvey; Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.).; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Internal Security.; Workers Alliance of America.; Anti-communist movements |z United States.; Articles.; Christian socialism |z United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Communism and religion |z United States.; Communist parties |z United States.; Communist trials |z United States.; Communists |z Ohio.; Communists |z United States.; Correspondence.; Examinations (documents); Labor leaders |z United States.; Memorabilia.; Miners |x Labor unions |z Harlan County (Ky.); Notes.; Pamphlets.; Papers (document genres).; Peace movements |z United States.; Photograph albums.; Photographs.; Political candidates |z New York (State) |z New York.; Political candidates |z Ohio.; Press releases.; Prisoners |z United States |v Correspondence.; Public relations and politics.; Reports.; Speeches.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 |x Protest movements.
- Series I: Education and Political Thought, 1926-1931
  Scope and Content Note
  The material mostly comprises course outlines, examinations, papers, and notes written by Arnold Johnson during his attendance at California Christian College, the Union Theological Seminary, and Columbia University Teachers College. Much of Johnson's writing reveals his christian socialist ideals and his association with "radical" causes. Of particular interest in this respect are the contents of folders 7 and 8, notes on the garment and steel workers strikes, and papers written for a course in christian ethics. Johnson spent much of his spare time at college putting his ideals into practice. He made street corner speeches and handed out leaflets in support of the 1929 garment workers strike in New York (ILGWU). Johnson's involvement in Sherwood Eddy's American Seminar (1929 and 1930), is also documented. Johnson took notes which provide an account of his first impressions of the communist way of life.
  - California Christian College, examinations, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - California Christian College, diploma, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sherwood Eddy Seminar, notes, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Union Theological Seminary, course outlines, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Union Theological Seminary, course outlines, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Union Theological Seminary, course notes and papers, 1929-1931 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Union Theological Seminary, notes - Garment Workers' and Steel Workers' Strikes, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Union Theological Seminary, Christian Ethics papers, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Union Theological Seminary, curriculum, 1929-1931 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Columbia University, Teachers College, notes, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Columbia University, Teachers College, MA Thesis “Social Responsibility in the Approaches to Curriculum Construction.”, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II: Early Political and Communist Party Activities, 1931-1947
  This series contains mostly articles (written by Johnson and others) and notes and speeches. Johnson's political activities before he joined the Communist Party USA (the years 1931-36) - his involvement with the National Miners Union in Harlan, Kentucky and with the Unemployed Leagues (particularly in Ohio) - are not well documented by contemporary material. There are many references, mostly brief, in newsclippings and biographical materials of later years which refer back to these experiences. They were important turning points in Johnson's political and personal life. The notebook located in Series V folder 19 helps to fill in some of the gaps.
  Johnson stayed in Ohio and continued working with the unemployed (in the Workers Alliance) after joining the Communist Party USA in 1936. Speeches, mostly delivered by Johnson on a weekly radio broadcast, are the most abundant form of material remaining from Johnson's years as Ohio Communist Party leader (1936-1947). Many relate to the political programs of the Communist Party as expressed in Johnson's candidatures for state Governor, Cleveland Board of Education, and Mayor of Cleveland. Other speeches document Johnson's presidency of the Ohio Workers Alliance, the Communist Party support of the war against Hitler, and, after the war, of the Soviet Union.
  - Harlan and Bell, Kentucky, National Miners Union, articles (Johnson and others), 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ohio and National Unemployed Leagues, and Workers Alliance, clippings and articles (Johnson and others), 1933-1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Notes on CP, Marx, Lenin and U.S. history, ca.1935 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - OHIO CP Yearbook, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Speeches, 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Runs for Office, clippings, correspondence, pamphlets, 1943-1946 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Speeches - radio, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Speeches - radio, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Speeches - radio, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Speeches - radio, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Clippings, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Series III: Smith Act and Consequences, 1947-1957
  This series contains correspondence, clippings, flyers, press releases, pamphlets, speeches and reports. Arnold Johnson's Smith Act trial, he and his wife Aurelia's response to these proceedings and to the following years in jail, and the rally of support both for Johnson and against the Smith Act (the Citizens Emergency Defense Conference) are all well documented. The prison correspondence between Arnold and Aurelia Johnson is comprehensive, and although muted by prison regulations provides insight into Johnson's integrity of character, his unshaken beliefs in the freedom of speech and civil rights, and in the communist cause. The strength of the Johnsons' commitment to one another, and to their beliefs held in common, are also reflected in this correspondence. Other correspondence of particular interest is found in folders 6, 10 and 16. Folder 6 contains both the Johnson's reaction to the indictment in 1951. At the time of his arrest Arnold Johnson was representing the Civil Rights Congress in Pittsburgh. Johnson's christian socialist roots, his ability to maintain a dialog with those of different convictions, and the discomfort many outside the CP felt with the Smith Act proceedings, are all reflected in the positive response to his plight from inside and outside the Communist Party. Many with church associations responded to pleas for financial aid at risk to their own reputations. The letters from Marion C. Frenyear (pastor of a Congregational Church in South Hartford, NY), in particular, reflects this. Other principal correspondents include Aurelia Johnson, Elizabeth Hall (wife of Gus Hall), and Clifford T. McAvoy (Citizens Emergency Defense Conference - CEDC). There is 1 brief letter from W. E. DuBois amongst the CEDC correspondence. Prominent Communist Party correspondents include Eugene Davis (letter of thanks to Aurelia Johnson, 1955), and George A. Meyers (1955). The letter from Meyers describes his release from prison, and is quite detailed.
  - Clippings, press releases - college ban on Arnold Johnson (speaker), 1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Speeches, statements - Arnold Johnson as National Legislative Director of CPUSA, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Clippings - crackdown on Communist Party, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Articles in Political Affairs, by Arnold Johnson, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Smith Act, “Facts on the Trial of the 12”, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and speeches - Smith Act arrest, trial, and sentencing, 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Clippings - Smith Act indictment, bail, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Indictment, Trial “Statement of Proceedings” (1951), and “Statement before Sentencing”, 1951-1953 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Citizens Emergency Defense Conference - correspondence, clippings, pamphlets, 1951-1953 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence - others response to arrest and appeals for financial assistance, 1951-1954 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Speeches (and comment), including Rosenburg Trial, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence with Elizabeth Hall (Gus Hall' wife), 1952-1956 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Citizens Emergency Defense Conference - Smith Act Trial Reports, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Citizens Emergency Defense Conference - correspondence, printed material, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Smith Act - sentence appeal, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence - prison regulations, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Prison correspondence - Aurelia Johnson, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Prison correspondence - Arnold Johnson, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Prison correspondence - Aurelia Johnson, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Prison correspondence - Arnold Johnson, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Prison correspondence - Aurelia Johnson, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Prison correspondence - Arnold Johnson, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Smith Act - pamphlets, flyers, 1955-1958 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Smith Act indictment-fine payments, receipts, 1957-1976 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Series IV: Political Activities, 1957-1979